<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ exalted into His throne and the Scripture owned in its place.</title>
            <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33021</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12841542</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12841542</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94394</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56429)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94394)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1038:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ exalted into His throne and the Scripture owned in its place.</title>
                  <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 8: James Parnell.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggest by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Royal office.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Evidences, authority, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94394:1"/>
            <head>Chriſt Exalted INTO HIS THRONE, <hi>And the Scripture owned in its place.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His then is the meſſage that we have received of the Father, that God is light, and in him is no darkneſſe at all, if we walk in darkneſſe and ſay we have fellowſhip with him, we lye and doe not the truth, but if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, then have we fellowſhip one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſinne, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7. And this is the word which was in the beginning, by which all things was made, and in him was life, and his life was the light of men, <hi>John</hi> 1. 1, 2, 3, 4. By which light all the holy men of God in the dayes of old were inſpired; By which light <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw the things that were done in the beginning, and wrote of them; Which word was a lampe unto <hi>Davids</hi> feet and a light unto his paths, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 105. Which light dwelt in the Prophets and holy men, by which they ſaw the day of Chriſt, and wrote of him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 6. and 60. 19. and ſpoke as they were moved by it, and by it ſaw the deceit, iniquities, and tranſgreſſions of Iſrael, and declared againſt it both in Prieſt people and Rulers, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the word of the Lord faithfully, whether they would hear or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94394:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Ezek</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Micha 3. Iſa.</hi> 56. And this word came unto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which was as a fire and a hammer in their bones, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20. 9. and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. 29. Which word in due time became fleſh and dwelt among the Apoſtles, and they ſaw the glory thereof as of the onely begotten Son of the Fa<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her ful<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of grace and truth, <hi>John</hi> 1. 14. whom <hi>John</hi> bears wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of to be the light of the world, who doth enlighten every-one that comes into the world, <hi>John</hi> 1. To which light <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to turne the mindes of the Heathen, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 17, 18. Which light is the condemnation of the world, who love darkneſſe rather then light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds are evill, and he that hates it hath it, though he will not bring <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deeds to it, by it to be proved, therefore his condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is. <hi>John</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 19. 20. 21. And there is a time light ſhines in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and darkneſſe comprehends it not, <hi>John</hi> 1. 5. And this is the cauſe why many <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it and are offended in it.</p>
            <p>And the there's a time light ſhines out of darkneſſe and darkneſſe flees away, and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> witneſſed the perfect day wherein the children of the day doe <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 42. 16. <hi>Mat. 4. 16. Eph.</hi> 5. 8. Which light is the true t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and gives the diſcerning of ſpirits, and diſcovers the works of darkneſſe, and manifeſts the deeds of darkneſſe, and by it the ſecrets of the heart are ſeen and hidden things ſearched out, and by it all things are made manifeſt, and whatſoever makes manifeſt is light, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 12. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 13. All which the naturall man knows not, and therefore cannot receive the things of God, but by this light is ſeen and judged, for by this light the ſpirituall man is able to diſcerne and judge the naturall man, but he himſelfe is judged of no man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14, 15. For this is the judge of the world, and by this the Prince of the ayre is judged whereſoever he rules, <hi>John</hi> 16. 11. And therefore at it rages, and ſtirres up his ſervants to perſecnte it, where it is made manifeſt, and ſo it is a ſtumbling ſtone and a rock of offence to the children of the world in whom the Prince of this world lodgeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 33, And of this word the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> bears witneſſe to be quick and powerfull and ſharper then a two edged ſword to the dividing aſunder betwixt the marrow and the bones, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 12. to which word the Apoſtle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the mindes of people within them from looking without for to finde it without, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. And from this ſame word the Apoſtles ſpoke forth the Scripture, which word was their guide, and rule, and teacher all along from the beginning, by which both the Apoſtles, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and the holy men was acted moved and carried forth in the power of it to declare that which by it they were taught, 1 <hi>John 1. 2. Pet.</hi> 1. 21. And this is the free grace of God which bringeth ſalvation and hath appeared to all men, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12. Which is their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation who doe deſpite unto it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 29. But this was the Saints teacher, by which they were taught to deny all ungodlineſſe and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, and to live godlily, righteouſly, and ſoberly in this preſent evill world, and this is the anoynting, which teacheth all things freely, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94394:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is truth and no lye, and leads into all truth, and he that knows this need no man to teach him, but is come the end of mans teachitg, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 27. Unto which the Prophet was come, and therefore called freely, <hi>Come buy wine and milke without money or price, why ſpend you your money for that which is not bread, or your labour for that which profiteth not? Iſa.</hi> 55. 1, 2, 3. And from this the Apoſtles ſpoke freely, not coveting any mans ſilver or gold, but as they freely had received freely they gave, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 33. And whoſoever ſpeaks from this ſpeaks freely, and its miniſtry leads to the end of teaching, and here let all fleſh keep ſilence before the Lord, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
            <p>And let all Hirelings, and greedy Shepheards, ſtop their mouths who cry peace peace to them that put into their mouths, but if not, they even prepare war againſt them, and ſuch like the Prophet in the light ſaw, and by it teſtified againſt them, <hi>Mich.</hi> 3. 5. And all this the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bears teſtimony of, which was ſpoken from the light, but is not the light, nor the word, nor the life, nor the Judge, nor the Rule, nor the guide nor the tryer of ſpirits, for all this belongs to Chriſt, who is the diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 1, 2. who is the light, <hi>John</hi> 8. 12. who is the word, <hi>John</hi> 1. 14. who is the life, <hi>John</hi> 14 6. who blamed the Phariſes that thought in the Scriptures to finde eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, but would not come unto him that they might have life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 39, 40. who is the anoynting, who is the guide and teacher, and the Rule, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. 27. who when we are going to the right hand or to the left, cryes, this is the way walk in it, <hi>Iſa</hi> 30. 21. Of which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a true Declaration ſpoken from this word of truth, of which light every one hath a meaſure, which unto them is the free gift of God to profit withall, which light in the conſcience reproves for ſin and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and manifeſts the deceit of the heart, and checks the creature when it ſwears, or lyes, or doth amiſſe, telling it that it ſhould not doe ſo, and calls for repentance and amendment of life, and leads unto the ſame as it is owned and followed, and as many as receives it receives power to become the Sons of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 12. and 1. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 4. But he that doth evill hates the light and will not bring his deeds to it by it to be proved and to him it is condemnation, but he that loves the light brings his deeds to the light, that it may manifeſt them whether they be wrought in God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 20, 21. But of this light you people and Teachers of the world are ignorant, and ſo are doting upon the Scripture without with your dark mindes, therewith the blinde Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſeeking for life where it is not to be found, but will not come to Chriſt the light that you might have life, but would caſt him out of his throne, and exalteth Scripture above him, calling them the judge and the light, and the word, and the life, and the rule, and the guide, and thus with your dark mindes you would take the Authority from Chriſt, and would give it unto the dead letter, which is but a declaration of theſe things; And thus your leaders cauſe you to erre, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 12. for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94394:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their own ends, becauſe of the Scripture they make an Idoll to get mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by adding their own meanings, interpretations, and conſtructions upon them, which is all the conceivings and imaginations of their own hearts, by which they lead you in blindneſſe, ever learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth in your hearts, but are loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king without, doting without in the letter, acting and imitating out of the light for life, and ſo in darkneſſe doing your own works, which<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 6, 7. Iſa. 1. 12. Mat. 15. 9. John 4. 22.</note> are not required at your hands, but are for condemnation by the light, and ſo in vaine are you worſhipping a God whom ye know not, crying up his Ordinances, and crying up his Commands, and crying up the Scripture, exalting it in the place of Chriſt, and thus coming neere him with your lipps and your hearts far from him, ſtill living in the corrupt ſinfull nature, ignorant of the free grace of God which ſhould lead you to repentance and amendment of life, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 5: 8. And becauſe we doe witneſſe this myſtery, which hath been hid from ages and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, now made manifeſt in us, which is Chriſt within the hope of glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 26, 27. who is the light of the world, who doth enlighten eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that cometh into the world, who is the true Shepheard, <hi>John</hi> 10. and the true teacher no more to be removed into a corner, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 20.<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2. 27.</note> who is the anoynting, who teacheth all things and is the end of mans teaching; therefore your miniſtry of the letter, who make a trade and a gaine of the letter, by idolizing it, and ſetting it up in the roome of Chriſt, by taking the Authority from Chriſt and applying it to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that your mindes, who are taught by them, may the more be drawn without to look at it and Idolize it, expecting life and ſalvation by it, and no hope without it, that they may the longer make merchandize of you, and ſtill uphold their trade, and gaine by it, doe now ſee that this our doctrine of Chriſt to be all in all, and that without him we can doe nothing, <hi>John</hi> 15. 5. but that by him we can doe all things without the help of Scripture or any thing elſe without, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 13. and that there is no other name under heaven by which we can be ſaved, but that he is able to ſave to the utmoſt all that ſhall come unto God by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. And that he is the word, and the Scripture is not, and that he is the light, and the Scripture is not, and that he is the rule and guide, and teacher and judge, and the Scripture is not, but a declaration of him to be ſo, and that the Scripture all along witneſſeth with our Doctrine to be one with it, and theirs to be another Doctrine, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will not maintaine, but the Scripture is againſt, and is onely brought in for lucres ſake to ſatisfie their own carnall ends, that they may bear rule by their means, as the falſe Prophets did before them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. 30, 31.</p>
            <p>And this light all along makes them manifeſt in all their colours and falſe covers, ſo that they cannot hide themſelves from being Deceivers and alſo this they doe know, that if every one come to know and finde a teacher within them, which doth teach them the will of God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94394:3"/>
and doth enable them for to obey it, ſo that they need no man to teach them, then indeed they will no longer ſpend their monyes upon them for that which is not bread, nor their labour for that which profiteth not, and will be a prey unto them no longer; ſo not onely their craft and trade, and Idol, will faile them, but alſo their great gaine and riches will be taken from them, and all their honour and ſame and dignity will come to nought; therefore they in their hot rage, and fierceneſſe, t and enmity of their ſpirits, doe ſet themſelves to oppoſe this ligis whereſoever it is made manifeſt, and perſecuting the publiſhers of this Doctrine, railing againſt them as deceivers, and ſeducers, and bringers in of falſe lights, and ſuch as deny the Scripture, and would rob it of it Authority and give it to a light within them (which the Prieſts call a naturall light) and inſufficient to lead to ſalvation without the help of Scripture and other outward helps, and ſo would ſet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture above the light of Chriſt, ſaying among themſelves, if we let go the Authority of Scripture then all is gone, (that is to ſay) take away our Idoll, then take away our maintenance, then down with out Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry: So here is clear the foundation they ſtand upon, and this is the cauſe why they call the Scripture their foundation, and ſo all this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which they put upon the Scripture they take from Chriſt, who alone is the foundation of the faithfull, of whom the Scripture is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and ſo we doe own it by the ſame which gave it forth, which unto us doth open it and reveal it, and manifeſts them to be out of the life of it, and ſo by the life thereof are judged and condemned, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is proved; And though they call it the word, yet in the ſame it doth witneſſe againſt them, and witneſſe Chriſt to be the word before the Scripture was written, <hi>John</hi> 1. And though they call the Scripture the light, yet in the ſame it doth witneſſe againſt them, and witneſſeth Chriſt to be the light before the Scripture was written, and is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all that ſhall come unto God by him, and they that climbe up any other way the ſame are thieves and robbers, <hi>John</hi> 10. 1. And therefore is not a naturall inſufficient light, as they that know him not doe report of him, and therefore ſhew themſelves to be as ignorant as the Phariſes, who onely ſuppoſed him to be the Son of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> yet wondred at his power, and the works that were done by<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 55, 56.</note> him, as theſe doe now wonder at the proſperity of this miniſtration of light, and to ſee how it prevailes upon the hearts of the people, ſo that they know not what to think of it, they are not able to encounter with it, but that they ſee it ſtrikes ſo much at their Diana, and lyes ſo hard at their foundation, ſo that it makes their building totter, therefore the Rulers Prieſts and Phariſes takes counſell together, ſaying one to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> another, <hi>if we let this people alone, all men will goe after them, and they wil draw away whole Nations;</hi> therefore they take the ſame courſe as ever the falſe Prophets did, joyning together with the earthly powers to make war with the Lamb, perſecuting, ſtocking, whipping, impriſoning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94394:4"/>
and ſhamefully intreating his meſſengers, whom the Lamb ſends forth to bear teſtimony of this light in peoples conſciences (where we have a witneſſe both in them that beleive and in them that periſh) and alſo ſtriving all the wayes they can, by their evill incenſing, lying, raylings, and falſe accuſings and reporting to defame this light, and leaven your mindes againſt it (that if it were poſſible) to put it out, that ſtill they might uphold their fathers kingdome of darkneſſe, and bear rule by their means over the blinde, carrying captive the mindes of people, but who is able to make war with the Lamb, or who ſhall withſtand the day of his coming? <hi>Saul, Saul, it is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks;</hi> And though they call the Scripture their Rule and guide, yet in this it wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth againſt them, to be in <hi>Caines</hi> way, and <hi>Balaams</hi> way, and in the gaine ſaying of <hi>Core,</hi> and ſo have not God, <hi>Jude 11. 2 Iohn</hi> 9. but are found to be the generation who are borne after the fleſh, perſecuting them that are borne after the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 29. And though they call the Scripture their Rule and guide, yet they receive not power from it to enable them to walk according to it, but are altogether erring from it, in any thing that croſſeth ſelfe, but as many as receive the light re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives power to follow it, and come out of the corrupt ſinfull nature, which they live in who know not the light, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 12. And here the light is above the Scripture; and though they ſay the Scripture is the Judge and tryer of ſpirits, yet in the ſame it witneſſeth againſt them to be lyars, and bears witneſſe of Chriſt to be the Judge and tryer and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the heart and diſcerner of the thoughts, <hi>Heb. 4. 12. Rom. 1. 16. 1 Pet.</hi> 4. 5. and that whatſoever makes manifeſtation is light, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 13. therefore that which makes manifeſt falſe ſpirits is the light, and not the letter, which light manifeſted and diſcovered falſe ſpirits before the Scripture was written; and alſo though they ſay the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the Judge and tryer of ſpirits, yet by the Scripture they cannot diſcerne or Judge of ſpirits, elſe what makes all this difference in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt them who profeſſe to try ſpirits by the Scripture, and profeſſe it to be their Rule, and ground their judgements upon it; yet are ſo confuſed in the ſame, and never a one knowes which is the truth, when as the way is but one; ſo that it followes that they have nothing but the Scripture without, are ſtill without in darkneſſe and confuſion, as all thoſe appears to be who call the Scripture their Rule, and guide, and Judge, and tryer of ſpirits, and yet knowes not the truth, but are jangling and wrangling, and arguing, and diſputing, and contending about the Scripture, every one with a ſeveral judgement upon it, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this diſtraction is not in the Scripture, for it was ſpoken from one and all agrees in one; therefore you that ſo profeſſe the Scripture, ſee if you can finde it out by the Scripture, and ſee where you are, but they that are in the light have fellowſhip one with another, 1 <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1. 7. and are of one heart and one ſoule, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 32. and all agree in one, and are Epiſtles wrote one in anothers heart, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 2. and by the light
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94394:4"/>
they try and diſcerne falſe ſpirits, and in it are able to judge them, and open the Scriptures without wreſting adding or diminiſhing, and by it doe know they are of God, becauſe they love one another with the ſame love with which Chriſt loved them, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. it is not ſuch love which is to day and to-morrow croſſe the will and it is turned into wrath and anger, nay that love ſtands in the corrupt will, but this love ſtands in the bond of peace which doth indure; and here againe the light is above the Scripture, and though they ſay the light muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Scripture, yet in this the Scripture doth witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and bears witneſſe of Chriſt to be the light of the world, <hi>and doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world;</hi> and they that could never read letter of the book have this light, which is ſufficient to teach them and lead them into all truth after they come to the knowledge of it, and from this light the Scripture was ſpoken, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 21. and without this light none can read the Scripture with underſtanding, and here the light is before the Scripture, and out of it all the children of darkneſſe are ſhut with their buſie mindes and vaine contending ſpirits; and though they ſay they muſt receive life and ſalvation from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, yet in this the Scripture witneſſeth againſt them, and teſtifies of Chriſt to be the alone fountaine of life and ſalvation, <hi>and that there is no other name under heaven by which we can be ſaved, Pſal.</hi> 30. 9 and 144. 10. And that the Pharſees had the Scripture yet had not the light nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could ſee that he was the Chriſt though the Scripture bare teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of him, or either would come unto him for life and ſalvation, but truſted in the ſcripture thinking there to find eternall life and therein found it not. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 39, 40. As all you are now who are ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the living among the dead, and here againe the light is above the Scripture, which light is within us the hope of glory. <hi>Coll</hi> 1. 26, 27 and thoſe that cannot witneſſe this are in the reprobation, though they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> have the Scripture without, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. and from it we receive life and ſalvation, and from no other, and this alone is our guide, teacher, Judge, and Law giver, if we never ſee letter, <hi>Luke 1. 79. Iohn 6. 45. Iſa.</hi> 33. and this alone is the ground and foundation of our faith and hope, by which we are made able to to cry Abba Father, 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 11. Rom.</hi> 8. 15. And here it is not ſelf that judgeth or condemns, but Chriſt that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 20. and it is not ſelfe that juſtifies us, but Chriſt that liveth in us; and here Chriſt is exalted into his throne, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture owned in its place, without contempt or undervaluing. And they found the Miniſters of Antichriſt, who would caſt Chriſt out of his throne, and take the Scripture out of its place to exalt above him, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to it that Authority which alone belongs unto him for their own by ſecret ſelfe ends, ſo that in that they apply ſuch Authority to the Scripture, they in the ſame rob Chriſt of it, and undervalues him, as the Phariſes did, who thought in the Scriptures to finde eternal life, but would not come to Chriſt that they might have life, in whoſe ſteps ye and your teachers are now found profeſſing Chriſt in words, but in life
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94394:5"/>
denying him, and therefore muſt be judged and condemned by him, as they was. And if you Prieſts doe alledge there is a falſe light, as well as a true light, I Anſwer, that is it in you which blinds your minds ſo that you cannot receive this Goſpel, but from you it is hid, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. 4. And therefore you bring another Goſpel, calling the foure Books <hi>Matthew Marke Luke</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Goſpel: in which theſe foure Books will witnes againſt you, and beare witneſſe of Chriſt to be the Goſpel which is the power of God unto ſalvation: who is the Lambe of God ſlaine from the foundation of the world who came to take away the ſins of the world; and bleſſed are they thar are not offended in him, <hi>Iohn 1. 26. and verſ 13. Luke</hi> 7. 23 and alſo that is a falſe light in you which leades you into the forme or reſemblance or outward ſhew of holineſſe but denies the life and power, 2 <hi>Timo.</hi> 3. 5. and to profeſs the Scripture no be your Rule but in life and practice deny it, and to be ſhort leades into a profeſſion without poſſeſſion but that which leades into the life and power is no falſe light for it leades into the poſſeſſion before the profeſſion, and ſo the profeſſion is from the poſſeſſion, but your profeſſion is from anothers poſſeſſion, and ſo boaſts in anothers line by which you beguile both your ſelves and others; and therefore in that you goe about to arme your ſelves with the Scripture, to oppoſe the light by exalting it above the light, thinking thereby to debaſe the light and ſo to keepe peoples minds from the light that they may ſtill remaine in darkneſſe and blindneſſe under you. You do but in the ſame bring a weapon to cut off your own heads, and raiſe a war to deſtroy your ſelves, and increaſe more light to the people and manifeſt your ſelves odious, and to be the blind guides of the Nation; who are to be denyed and turned away from us, deceivers to be held as accurſed who<note place="margin">2 Iohn 9. 10.</note> bring another Doctrine in oppoſition to the true Doctrine which is held forth in the Scripture, for the Scripture and the light agrees in one, from both which you are ſhut with jangling contentious ſpirits by which you would wreſt the Scripture out of its place, to claſh againſt its Orignall; thereby to uphold your father Antichriſts Kingdome, and therein doe the more manifeſt your ſelves to be the miniſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, who under profeſſion of the true Chriſt doe oppoſe him and make war with him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13, 14, 15. but your weapons are weak, as is dayly made manifeſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Parnell.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
